I merely believe that
我只是觉得人活着
a person must excel in one thing
一定要有一件
in his life.
能做好的事情
He must know
不能不知道
what he wants.
自己想要什么
And he can't become
更不能成为一个
a good-for-nothing.
一无是处的人
What about you?
你呢
Why did you join the Navy?
你为什么要当海军
When I was transferred
从陆大转到
from the Army University to the S.M.C.,
电雷学校的时候
many people told me
很多人都说
it was a shortcut for promotion.
这是一条晋升的捷径
But it isn't.
但是去海军并不是捷径
Our country's navy force
我们的海军
is weak.
一点儿也不强大
But why do you want to be part of it?
那你为什么还要当海军
To date,
到今天为止
the main force of our naval fleet
我们的海军舰队主力
are antique warships
大部分仍是
inherited from the Qing Dynasty.
清朝遗留的军舰
They are outdated,
技术落后
low-speed and firepower-weak.
航速低 火力弱
But the world maritime powers
可其他的海洋强国
have been
已经发生了
through revolutionary evolution.
革命性的变化
Obsession with big warships and cannons
大舰巨炮主义
has been abandoned.
正在被抛弃
A new mode of carrier-based aircraft
利用舰载机
striking the enemy's fleets
打击对方舰队的新模式
is more and more dominating battlefields.
正在主宰海战战场
These countries have many battleships,
他们有大量
cruisers, destroyers
用先进动力和武器
and even aircraft carriers
装备起来的
equipped with advanced propelling system
战列舰 巡洋舰 驱逐舰
and weapons.
甚至是航空母舰
Including Japan.
这其中也包括日本
It has been 40 years
距离甲午海战
since the First Sino-Japanese War.
已经过去了四十年
and our country's navy made no progress.
我们还在原地踏步
Japan had developed into
日本已经一跃
a maritime power.
成为了海洋强国
The tonnage of its warships
他们的海军吨位数
is well over 1.15 million tons.
超过了一百一十五万吨
Ours is
而我们只有
poorly 60,000 tons.
区区的六万吨
That is like
这简直就是
an ant fighting with an elephant.
大象和蚂蚁的区别
The strength disparity is appalling.
实力悬殊到令人心痛
That is why
也正是因为这份心痛
I decided to do my part in the Navy.
我才想要出一份力
Your attitude is completely different from
你说这些话的样子
that
和你在四所的时候
when you were in the Fourth Station.
完全不一样
Because this is my ideal.
因为这是我的梦想
I used to think
我以前以为
many simple
人活这一辈子
and joyful things
就应该做很多很多
could make a person
又简单
feel satisfied.
又快乐的事情
For instance,
比如
I wear a pair of shoes I like today.
穿了一双喜欢的鞋子
I feel lucky it is not a rainy day.
今天刚好没有下雨
As I come back home,
回到家里
dinner I like
桌子上
is ready.
刚好是我喜欢的饭菜
I have watermelon with my family
夏天和家人们一起
in the courtyard in summer.
在天井吃西瓜
I pick up osmanthus flowers
秋天
on the ground in fall.
去捡满地的桂花
Now I realize
我现在知道
a person should have
人活着
something to dream of.
还应该有向往的事情
Maybe
这大概
this is the so-called ideal
就是你所说的
you defined.
梦想
Come on, brother.
哥 快点儿
Coming.
来了来了
I get it.
我来吧
Let's go.
走
Brother, did you notice
哥 你发现了没有
while
刚刚那两个人
they were talking,
说话的时候
their eyes were twinkling.
眼睛里都闪着光
Luo Minmin
连骆珉敏那种
is a careless girl.
平时稀里糊涂的人
But she got serious just now.
一下子就认真了起来
You are right.
是
Yuansheng is not only handsome
你说向警官这种
and family-prominent,
长得帅 家世好
but also knowledgeable and kind.
学识渊博又温柔
To be his girlfriend
谁能跟他在一起
is a very happy thing.
那可真是太幸福了
Minmin is an above-average girl.
可是咱家珉敏也不差
Of course.
我姐姐当然也不差
But they two
可是他们两个
are far different.
也太不一样了
Officer Xiang is like a tree.
向警官就像棵大树
Minmin is like a flower.
骆珉敏就像朵小花
That's why
所以呀 他们才能发现
they can find
对方有
each other's unique good qualities.
自己却没有的优点
Yuansheng appreciates
大树羡慕小花长在地下
Minmin's lively personality.
热热闹闹
Minmin admires
小花觉得
Yuansheng
大树头顶就是天空
as an aspirational man.
了不起得很
Though different,
他们是不一样
they complement each other.
但这不也挺好的吗
Agreed.
挺好的挺好的
OK, we need to hurry up.
行了 快走吧
The rain has eased.
雨小了
I have to go.
我也该走了
When will your train depart?
几号的火车
At one o'clock tomorrow noon.
明天中午一点
The captain and I will see you off
那我和队长他们
tomorrow.
一起去送你
Please don't.
不用了
Someone will take me to the train station.
明天有人送我去火车站
Let's bid farewell now.
就在这里告别吧
Xiang Yuansheng,
向远生
why did you come here?
你今天为什么要来四所
Did you come here for the police manual?
真的是因为警员手册吗
But,
可是
during the time you worked here,
你在四所的这段时间
you never
从来没有翻看过
read it.
警员手册
I was thinking,
我想
maybe
以后可能
we won't meet each other anymore.
再也见不到面了
But fortunately,
不过幸好
I had spoken out what I wanted to say.
该说的话我也说出来了
I saw
想见的人
the one I want to see.
我也见到了
Mr. Hua.
华先生
I was looking for you in Jinmen Hotel.
我跑了趟金门饭店找你
But you weren't there.
没找着
I guess
我一猜
you are here.
你就在这儿
I'm sorry.
不好意思
You are under arrest.
你被逮捕了
You are on suspicion of communist membership.
侦查队怀疑你是共产党
This is the warrant issued
这是淞沪警备司令部的
by the Shanghai Garrison Command.
逮捕令
Do you have proof?
有证据吗
Of course, I have.
当然
I will show you
我会一样一样地
one by one.
证明给你看
We can begin with Xiang Yuansheng,
就从向远生这个化名
your alias.
开始
Captain,
队长
should we take the girl as well?
这女的也带走吗
Yes.
一起带走
I will interrogate them
明天天亮的时候
tomorrow morning.
我亲自提审
Yes, sir.
是
Take them away.
带走
Don't touch me.
松开我
Don't move.
别动
Let me go.
放开
Heading back.
走
Captain Wei,
魏队长
is Luo Minmin
骆珉敏也有
a communist suspect?
共产党嫌疑吗
We suspect
侦查队怀疑
she is your accomplice.
她是你的同党
So tell me.
那你解释一下
Why didn't she go home at night?
这么晚了她不回去
Did she have a meeting
跟你待在这儿
with you?
开会呀
I thought you knew our relationship.
我以为你已经看出来了
Miss Luo is my girlfriend.
骆警官是我的女朋友
We didn't plan
本来我们不打算
to make the relationship public.
公开关系的
At least not now.
起码不是现在
Now that you came across us,
但既然已经被你遇到了
we don't need to conceal that anymore.
我们也就不隐瞒了
I met my girlfriend
我想在离开前
one last time
再跟自己的女朋友
before I left the city.
见一面
It is reasonable, right?
这很正常吧
You...
你
and her?
跟她
We have a lot of time
你和我的问题
to solve the problem between us.
可以慢慢解决
If you don't have enough proof
但如果你没有
to say
足够的证据
Miss Luo is a communist,
证明骆警官也有问题
you should let her go home.
请你尽快放她回家
Sorry.
对不起
We tracking team
侦查队
got procedures to go through.
有侦查队的程序
If she is innocent,
如果她没有问题
she will be released.
我自然会放她回家
Hello.
喂
Secretary Guo,
郭秘书长
it's Wei Daiqing.
魏岱擎
Hua Zhen has been arrested.
华桢已经被逮捕
He is taken into custody
人现在关在
in a cell of the Garrison Command.
警备司令部的牢房里
What should we do next, secretary?
请秘书长指示
His family will get the information soon.
华家很快就会收到消息
They will take him back
他们一定想把华桢
to Nanjing.
带回南京
You go as planned.
你就做好你该做的事
The rest
其他问题
is not your concern.
不必担心
Yes, sir.
明白
Captain.
队长
We have brought
我们把华桢放在饭店的
Hua Zhen's all belongings
所有私人物品
from his hotel.
都拿过来了
Nothing special.
没有发现什么问题
Miss Luo.
骆警官
Luo Minmin.
骆珉敏
Your father
你的父亲
is running a photo studio.
开了一家骆记照相铺子
Your mother died
你母亲在你八岁的时候
when you were eight years old.
就过世了
Your brother
哥哥骆天祥
Luo Tianxiang was conscripted in 1932.
民国二十一年被抓了丁
After he deserted and came back,
逃跑回来之后
he didn't have regular employment.
就没了正经工作
He was often blackmailed by scumbags.
经常受到流氓的勒索
And then
好容易
he did odds and ends in a mahjong parlor.
去了一家麻将馆打杂
But not long,
可是前不久
the owner of the mahjong parlor was dead.
麻将馆的老板又死了
He lost his job once again.
他就再次失了业
Your younger sister Luo Qinqin
你妹妹骆勤芹
is in senior year of high school.
现在就读高中三年级
According to my calculation, Miss Luo,
我算了一下骆警官
minus living expenses,
你们全家的收入
the rest of your family's income merely
除了吃喝拉撒之外
affords your younger sister's tuition fee.
仅够付你妹妹的学费
And you, Luo Minmin.
还有你 骆珉敏
You performed bad in school time, and
从小成绩就不好
failed three police admission exams.
考了三年警察都没考上
This year, you were recruited and ranked
今年才堪堪以最后一名
at the bottom of the admission list.
勉强及格
You are not smart.
没有任何过人之处
You don't excel in anything.
没有擅长的事
You are neither pretty
谈不上姿色
nor talented.
也看不出来才华
What do you want to say?
你想说什么
I want to say that
我想说
you know
华桢的身世
Hua Zhen's family background well.
你也是知道的啊
But it doesn't mean his prominent identity
虽然他那些光环
can make him immune to investigation.
也没什么了不起的
The Establishment won't prosper forever.
权贵没有常青树
But, given his family background,
但是以他的条件
do you think he would
你以为他会看得上
fall on an ordinary girl?
一个平庸的女子
Does he really like you
他是真心喜欢你
or just use you
还是想利用你
and the relationship
和你的关系
to cover something?
来掩饰一些什么
The answer is obvious.
答案是显而易见的
God
老天爷
doesn't always like
不一定只喜欢
a smart and pretty girl.
聪明漂亮的小孩儿
Sometimes he likes a dumb girl
也有喜欢
as well.
笨小孩儿的时候
So does Xiang Yuansheng.
向远生也一样
I'm certain
我相信
he likes me.
他就是喜欢我
I know him very well.
以他的为人
He is not who you think.
不屑于像你所说的那样
He wouldn't attain any goal
用这么幼稚的行为
by doing naive behavior.
而达到某种目的
We just
我和他
like each other
就是简简单单的
simply.
互相喜欢
It looks to me that
看来
you've never
你从来没有过
experienced anything like it.
真心地喜欢上一个人
You have no idea
蠢
how stupid you are!
而不自知
Dad,
爸爸
I have it prepared
华桢的问题
to deal with the problem of Hua Zhen.
我已经安排好了
M.M.A. agreed if Shanghai allows it,
部里说只要上海放人
he would be transferred to the Ministry
他就可以
of Military Affairs for interrogation.
回到军政部受审
We still have time.
这会儿时间还早
I'm going to set off to Shanghai.
我马上出发
I know what you are worried about.
我知道您在担心什么
I have got everything in order.
我已经安排好了
Don't worry about it.
您放心吧
He is in 20s
二十几岁的人了
and still acts childish.
不让人省心
He should be cultivated more.
简直是不可造就
He was out of line this time.
华桢这次确实出格
But he will never help out any communists.
但肯定不会帮共产党
I'm certain of that.
关于这一点您放心
You must cope with it carefully.
事情一定要谨慎处理
He must learn a lesson
这回要让他
this time.
好好长个记性
Mr. Hua,
华先生
your tutor
这是我特地为你准备的
stayed in this cell before.
你老师待过的屋子
Do you enjoy it?
住得还舒服吧
This is your statement of confession.
这是你的认罪书
If you press your fingerprint
如果你在正式庭审之前
on it
肯在这个认罪书上
before the court hearing,
盖手印的话
I'll intercede on your behalf.
我会替你求情
Don't waste your time.
别硬挺着了
Nobody will help you
以你这个罪名
plead not guilty.
是不会有人来帮你的
Did we investigate
骆警官的家人
Miss Luo's family?
都调查过了吗
Not yet.
还没有
So,
走
we should get them all here for interrogation.
那就都抓来一起审审喽
Why is Luo Minmin still in custody?
骆珉敏为什么还在这儿
'Cause I have authority
因为我有权力
to keep her here.
不让她离开
I just talked with Miss Luo.
我刚才跟骆警官聊了聊
The little girl
这小姑娘
is unbelievably naive.
实在是太天真了
She thought
她竟然以为
you really crushed on her.
你真的喜欢她
I told her the good and the bad
我跟她好好分析了一下
of the current situation.
现实的情况
I hope she will acknowledge the fault
希望骆警官
she made.
能够幡然醒悟吧
I intend to keep her
而且我打算
in her cell for a long time,
一直把她留在这里
When I call her,
随叫
she has to come.
随到
'Cause I need to interrogate her
因为我要随时随地
whenever I want to.
找她了解情况
Mr. Hua,
华先生
I know
我知道你这个人
you never suffered setbacks.
从来没有受过挫折
As a man,
但是但凡是个人
you will use up your good luck
他的好运气
one day.
就会用光的
I mean it.
真的
Think about
你好好体会一下
what the real world is.
什么是真实的世界
Director An,
安处长
It will be a long time
今日一别
before we meet again.
不知何时才能再见了
Stay in touch.
常联系
OK.
知道了
What's more,
还有
if you need
在上海
any assistance
要是有什么
in Shanghai,
必须要办的事情
just call us.
给我们打电话
We will help you.
兄弟们都在呢
Come to me
你们到苏州的时候
as you go to Suzhou.
别忘了来找我啊
We will.
一定
OK, I need to go.
行了你们回去吧
OK.
好
Goodbye, Director An.
那我们回去了 安处长
Take care, Director An.
慢走 安处长
Staff Chief Tong.
佟参谋长
Are you leaving?
准备要走了
Yes, Sir.
对
I came to say farewell to others.
过来跟大家道个别
Then I'm going to pick up Hua Zhen.
然后去接华桢
You don't
华桢
need to do that.
就不要去接了
Captain Wei arrested him
今天凌晨
in this morning.
魏队长已经把他逮捕了
You did?
你逮捕华桢
Yes, sir.
是
What for?
什么原因
We believe
侦查队有理由
he is a member of the Communist Party.
怀疑他是共产党
Do you have proof?
有证据吗
Suspicion or certainty?
可能还是确定
It's almost certain.
基本上确定
He is Deng Mingyuan's accomplice.
他就是邓铭远的同党
Of course,
当然了
if you want
如果安处长
to see him
想在临走之前
before leaving,
见他一眼的话
I can arrange the visit.
这我还是可以安排的
I told Hua Zhen that
我告诉过华桢
If he has any association
如果他跟邓铭远
with Deng Mingyuan,
牵扯不清
our friendship
我跟他就没有
will end.
来往的必要了
This is my attitude.
现在我还是这个态度
I know
我知道
you got along with him
你跟他
in the Army University.
在陆大相处得不错
But now
但是现在
you can't do anything for him.
你也无能为力啊
His brother is
他哥哥已经在
on the way to Shanghai.
来上海的路上了
You don't have to delay yourself here.
你就别耽误你自己了
Captain Wei,
魏队长
you've been working so hard on him.
你努力了这么久
Finally, you got what you want.
终于得偿所愿
Congratulations.
恭喜啊
It is my duty
效忠党国
to stay loyal to our country.
责无旁贷
It has been almost nine hours
这从昨天晚上进去
since they were taken away
到现在这都
last night.
快九个小时了
Why are they still put in custody?
他们怎么还不放人
Yes, brother.
是啊 哥
My sis and Xiang
姐和向警官
are in real trouble, are they?
不会出事儿吧
His elder brother
他哥哥不是那什么
is the secretary of the Office of Aides, isn't it?
侍从室秘书吗
She is losing her mind
给丫头都急疯了
and talking foolishly.
开始胡言乱语了
I'm not.
不是
Yesterday,
我昨天真的
I heard Xiang said so with my own ears.
亲耳听向警官说的
He said his brother was
说他哥哥是什么
the Secretary of the Office of Aides,
侍从室秘书
and his dad was the Undersecretary of
他爸爸是什么
the Ministry of Military Affairs.
军政部次长
Are you crazy?
丫头你 你疯了吧你
If she's not crazy,
不是她疯了
Xiang Yuansheng is crazy.
就是向远生疯了
They don't believe me.
他们都不信我说的话
I don't want it.
我不喝
What she said is true.
她说的是真的
Although Xiang Yuansheng didn't tell it,
虽然向远生没有说过
it is a fact.
但确实是这样
Brat,
臭小子
Are you crazy too?
你也疯了吧
You're all crazy.
你们都疯了
Secretary Hua,
华秘书
it must be a tiring journey from Nanjing.
您从南京来一路辛苦了
Are you Captain Wei?
你就是魏队长
Yes, sir.
是
I'm Wei Daiqing, the leader of
我是警备司令部
the investigation team.
侦查队队长魏岱擎
Staff Chief Tong told me
佟参谋长吩咐过
you'd be attending the trial.
说您要全程参加会审
He ordered me to stay at your service.
关照我务必要全程陪同
I know very well
关于华桢的情况
about Hua Zhen.
我特别了解
I can report it to you in detail.
我可以详细向您汇报
It can wait.
再说吧
Come in.
请进
Uncle Tong.
佟叔叔
Hua Liang.
华梁啊
The long journey must have worn you out.
一路舟车劳顿
Glad you are here.
辛苦了
Before my departure,
我出门之前
my dad kept reminding me
我爸爸一再叮嘱我
to apologize to you
到了上海第一件事情
as soon as I arrived in Shanghai.
就是给您赔罪
I'm sorry
这件事情
to trouble you.
真的给您添麻烦了
Don't be a stranger.
见外的话咱就不多说了
Have a seat.
坐下聊
OK.
好
I can understand Undersecretary Hua.
华次长的心情我理解
I told your father on the phone
情况我在电话里
about the situation.
跟你父亲也大致讲过了
This time,
但是这次
Hua Zhen made a mistake of principle.
华桢犯的是原则问题
My dad won't interfere
我爸爸绝对不会
with any procedures.
干涉正常的程序
I think we can send
但是我觉得
Hua Zhen to Nanjing to be interrogated
可以让华桢回南京
by the Ministry of Military Affairs.
接受军政部的审讯
I think it's doable.
这还是可行的吧
Mr. He is in charge of
毕竟淞沪警备司令部
Shanghai Garrison Command.
在何部长管辖下
Hua Zhen is a relative of an officer
华桢又是军政部官员的
of the Ministry of Military Affairs.
直系亲属
Mr. He has known him well since he was little.
也是何部长看着长大的
We can manage to solve it internally.
我们可以内部解决
The situation
现在的情况
is much more complicated than it was
比我跟你父亲
when I spoke
打电话的时候
to your father.
棘手多了
Hua Zhen was classified
华桢已经被定性为
as a Category III political prisoner.
第三类政治犯
His trial will not
对他的审判
be carried out alone
就不只是
by the Military judiciary of
淞沪警备司令部军法处
the Shanghai Garrison Command.
单独来执行了
Are you saying
您的意思是
that he will undergo a joint trial?
要对他进行会审
Yes.
对
An interim joint trial Military Justice
现在已经成立了
commission has been set up.
临时军法会审委员会
In addition to the Command,
除了司令部
people from the Shanghai government,
还有上海市政府
the Shanghai party department,
上海市党部
and the second branch of
和江苏高级法院
the Jiangsu High Court will join the trial.
第二分院的人来参加
I'm afraid that
华桢
Hua Zhen couldn't go back to Nanjing.
恐怕回不去南京了
How could it be so serious?
怎么会这么严重呢
What evidence does
那个魏岱擎手里
Wei Daiqing have?
到底有什么证据
About this,
这个
I can not disclose.
我现在不便过多地泄露
The key to this case
其实这个问题的关键
does not lie in evidence
不在于证据
but the timing.
而在于这个时间点
Mr. He sentenced
邓铭远的案子
Deng Mingyuan to death
是你们何部长
himself.
亲自下令处决的
Immediately after his case was closed,
他的案子刚刚结束
Wei Daiqing claimed
魏岱擎就咬死了
Hua Zhen and Deng Mingyuan colluded.
华桢和邓铭远是同伙
What can you expect
你说
from Mr. He?
何部长该如何表态
Hua Liang,
华梁
I am an old friend of your father.
我是你父亲多年的老友
I have a question for you.
我还是想问一句
Did Hua Zhen
华桢到底
join the CPC?
会不会投了共产党
He has a great future awaiting.
他有大好的前途
He will never join any CPCs.
这个绝不可能
Brother.
哥
I'm sorry, Secretary Hua.
不好意思华秘书
I shouldn't have stayed here
本来我不应该留在这里
to get in your way.
妨碍你们说话
But I have to stay
但是按照司令部的规矩
according to the rules of the Command.
我也不得不留在这儿
Someone has your back.
你不是有人给你撑腰吗
You don't take orders from me.
我可管不了你
Do whatever
所以您爱干什么
you want.
就干什么
Could you open the door for me?
能帮我开下门吗
Had fun in Shanghai?
这次来上海玩高兴了
And ended up in prison.
把自己都玩到牢房里了
And they said
还弄了一顶
you were a communist.
共产党的帽子
Brother,
哥
you know where I stand.
我什么立场你清楚
Everything I did in Shanghai
我在上海
has nothing to do
做的每一件事儿
with politics.
都跟政治立场无关
I know
你是什么立场
where you stand.
我当然清楚
But it's no use talking about it now.
但是现在说这些没有用
I was planning to take you back to Nanjing,
我本来想把你带回南京
having you interrogated there,
咱们在军政部内部审讯
and solve the case internally.
解决掉
But it won't work.
但是行不通啊
Then I'll stand
那就在这儿
the interrogation here.
接受审讯
OK.
行
Good for you.
你想清楚了就行
I am here to tell you that since
我来就是想告诉你
you're not a communist, don't admit it.
既然不是那就咬定不是
Don't lose your footing.
别乱了阵脚
Dad misses you.
爸爸很挂念你
Things will work out.
事情一定会解决的
I got it.
知道了
Do you need to change,
想不想换身衣服
take a shower,
洗个澡
and have some palatable food?
吃点儿什么
I have a request.
有件事儿
I have a friend
我有个朋友
who is innocent and has been implicated.
被无辜牵连了进来
She's detained here too.
她也在这里
Could you take her out?
你方便把她带出去吗
I can't.
我不方便
I didn't travel a long way
我大老远跑过来
to rescue
不是为了解救
your friends.
你这帮狐朋狗友的
Now, I'm convinced you're fine.
你还真是没乱了阵脚啊
You're thinking about someone else.
到现在还想着别人
She's not just a friend.
她不是别人
I like her.
她是我喜欢的人
Are you serious?
你是认真的
Yes.
千真万确
She's a policewoman.
她是个警察
Her name is Luo Minmin.
叫骆珉敏
Secretary Hua,
华秘书
this is Miss Luo.
骆小姐给您带过来了
What else
还有什么
can I do for you?
我能帮得上的忙吗
See you at the trial.
我们审讯会上见吧
Please excuse me.
那就不送二位了
Feel free to come to me
有什么需要的话
if you need anything.
您随时找我
Thank you.
谢谢您
Are you
你就是骆珉敏骆警官
Yes, I am.
是
What's going on with Xiang Yuansheng?
向远生什么情况了
They won't let him go, huh?
他们还是不肯放过他吗
Did you mean Hua Zhen?
你是说华桢
Yes, Hua Zhen.
对 是华桢
Don't worry. He'll be all right.
放心吧 事情会解决的
I'll send you back to the police station.
我先送你回警察所
Thank you. I'll go back myself.
不用了 我自己回去吧
Hua Zhen asked me
华桢交代我了
to escort you back.
一定要亲自送你回去
And I want to see what the place is like,
而且我也想看看
which holds my brother
迟迟让我弟弟
from
不想回南京的地方
going back to Nanjing.
到底长什么样子
Please.
请吧
Thank you.
谢谢
Excuse me.
让一让
Here it is.
就是这儿
Minmin, are you all right?
姐 没事儿吧
Why are you two here?
你们怎么来了
This way.
这边
Director,
所长
this is Xiang Yuansheng's brother,
这是向远生的哥哥
Secretary Hua.
华秘书
He came
他是专程
from Nanjing.
从南京赶过来的
Nice to meet you, Secretary Hua.
华秘书好
I'm Zuo Ronghua, the police director.
敝人四所所长左荣华
Welcome you.
欢迎您光临
It's a great honor.
蓬荜生辉
Hello, Director.
你好 所长
Welcome.
欢迎
Please come in.
里 里边请
Get a glass of water.
倒杯水去
Don't bother.
不用麻烦了
I'll leave in a minute.
我马上就走
This is where Xiang...
这里就是小向
No.
不是不是
This is where Mr. Hua lives and works.
华公子生活工作的地方
Do you want me to show you around?
要不我带您参观一下
No.
不用了
Stool.
凳
Come on.
快 快
Water.
水
Have some water.
您 您喝水
Thanks.
谢谢
Let me
介
introduce you.
介绍一下
They are police officers here.
这些都是四所的警员
They are Mr. Hua's
华公子一块儿
colleagues.
出生入死的同僚
Introduce yourselves.
自我介绍一下
I'm Erbai.
四所警员 二白
I'm Sun Hongfa.
四所警员 孙鸿发
I'm Tian Dongbao.
四所警员 田冬宝
Mr. Hua,
华先生
I'm Chen Hao, the Captain.
我是四所的队长陈浩
Nice to meet you, Captain.
幸会 队长
How is he?
他现在情况怎么样
I'm here
我今天来呢
to tell you
就是跟大家说一下
about him.
他现在的情况
Shanghai Garrison Command suspected him
淞沪警备司令部
of being a communist.
怀疑他是共产党
Comm...
共
Communist?
共产党
And they have
而且已经掌握了
some evidence.
相关的证据
He can't be a communist.
他不可能是共产党吧
They said they had
他们说是掌握了一些
some evidence.
什么证据
But I have no idea.
但是我不知道
From what I know about my brother,
以我对我弟弟的了解
he would be the last to become a communist.
他不可能是共产党
Yeah.
是
Fortunately,
好在华桢现在的心态
Hua Zhen is optimistic.
很乐观
He wanted me to tell you
他让我跟大家
that he was fine.
报一个平安
Don't be upset.
不要太难受
Don't worry about him.
也不用太紧张
As his brother,
我作为他的哥哥
I would like to thank you
也要感谢大家
for taking care of him
这一个多月
for more than a month.
你们对他的照顾
Thank you.
谢谢
It's what we should do.
应该的
I hope you
希望大家
don't get involved in this.
不要被这件事情牵连
OK, that's all I wanted to say.
好 那我该说的都说了
I've given you his message.
他的话我也带到了
I won't bother you further.
就不耽误大家的时间了
See you.
再见
Secretary Hua...
华秘书长您
You came from far,
大老远来了
why not have a cup of water?
连口热水都没喝
What about...
要不然
Director, you are so kind.
所长 别客气了
Please stay.
请留步
Yes.
是
Mr. Hua.
华先生
I want to say something to you.
我还是想跟您说一句
Although he hasn't been here long,
他虽然来四所时间不长
we took him
但我们都把他
as one of us.
当作自己人了
If you need any help
如果您要是有什么事
from us,
需要我们帮忙
feel free to come to us.
您随时说
I hope he can
我希望他能
leave Shanghai safely.
平安离开上海
I will.
好
Now I understand
现在我终于明白
why Hua Zhen
华桢为什么
doesn't want to leave.
舍不得离开这儿
Captain Chen, thank you.
陈队长 谢谢你的好意
My pleasure.
应该的
Erbai,
二白
pinch me.
掐我一下
It was not a dream.
不是做梦
What an honor!
太荣幸了啊
I never thought
我左荣华
I'd meet
有生之年
the Secretary of the Office of Aides,
能见到侍从室的秘书
the son of the Undersecretary in my life.
军政部次长的长子
He doesn't have
这看看人家
any air of superiority.
一点儿架子都没有
Talking to him
就和人家说话就感觉
is like
那句成语
dreaming of the autumn wind.
如梦秋风
Dreaming of autumn wind?
秋风
Like bathing in the spring breeze?
如沐春风
By the way,
不是
shouldn't we care
咱现在是不是应该关心
what to do to help Xiang Yuansheng?
向远生怎么办
Why bother?
关注他干什么呀
His brother is here.
人家亲哥哥都来了
Director,
所长
can his brother
他哥哥
ask the Command to release Xiang?
能让警备司令部放人吗
Girl,
丫头
do you know who the secretaries
侍从室秘书
of the Office of Aides are?
那都是什么人哪
They serve Chairman Chiang
那是给蒋委员长
directly.
亲自办事儿的人
Not to mention
更何况
that his dad is the Undersecretary of
人家还有一个
the Ministry of Military Affairs.
军政部次长的亲爹
Don't worry.
放心吧
He will be all right.
没事儿
You can be rest assured.
一百个放心
But he said the leader of
可是他说
the investigation team has evidence.
侦查队的队长有证据
Will that work?
有证据有用吗
Even if there was more evidence,
再多的证据
it would not work
它不如某些人
as well as some people's words.
一句话管用
Do you feel that Xiang's brother
你觉不觉得
is better to get along with
小向他哥
than him?
比小向好相处多了
I don't think so.
我看不见得
Listen to yourself.
这口气
Who once had grudge against
也不知道是谁
Xiang Yuansheng
一开始跟人向远生
at the beginning?
还不对付
Who...
谁
Don't drink my water.
我倒的水你别喝
Don't...
不是
I will put that mug in my collection.
那杯子我得珍藏起来
Give it.
还  还给我
I borrowed the background documents
我从公安局
from the Public Security Bureau.
调了他们所有人的档案
None of them are communists.
没有发现有共党嫌疑的
Have you investigated every one of them?
所有人都查过了
Yes.
对
Their relatives?
他们的亲戚亲属
Investigated.
也都查过了
Could Chen Hao
这个叫陈浩的
ever intersect
以前的生活轨迹
with Hua Zhen
会不会跟华桢
before?
有什么交集
He was born in a village
这个人的老家
by the river in Fengxian.
在奉贤江边的小村子里
His parents are both fishermen.
父母都是普通的渔民
Neither of them could read.
不太识字
He graduated from
他自己是
the Zhejiang Police Academy.
从浙江警官学校毕业的
He has been working as a policeman
毕业之后就一直
in Shanghai since his graduation.
在上海当警察
Judging by the background documents,
至少从档案上来看
no connection
并没有发现
has been found
这个警察所
between the police station
和邓铭远之间
and Deng Mingyuan.
有直接的联系
Secretary Hua,
华秘书
do you suspect that,
您是在怀疑
other than Deng Mingyuan,
二少爷身边
there are other communists
除了邓铭远之外
around Hua Zhen?
还有其他的共产党吗
My brother
我这个弟弟
is 24 years old.
今年二十四岁了
Before coming to Shanghai,
在这次来上海之前
he had not done anything
从来没有过一次
that exceeds what is proper.
出格的行为
I wonder
我很好奇
what magic power
这个警察所
this police station has.
到底有什么魔力
How did it
让他一步一步地
take him off track step by step?
偏离轨道
I'm even more curious after reading this.
看完这些我更好奇了
Such a place.
这么一个地方
Such a group of people.
这样一群人
How did they attract him
他们凭什么
so much?
能把他留在这儿
Did Hua Liang surprise at
华梁是不是很惊讶
his setback?
他未能如愿哪
Yes.
是
He requested to be present at the trial.
唯一的要求 旁听会审
Secretary,
秘书长
what should I do?
属下该怎么做
Do you know
你知道
what is the most important link
在有罪论证的链条中
in a legal argument?
哪一环最重要吗
Evidence.
证据最重要
What if there is no evidence?
如果没有证据呢
Secretary Guo,
报告郭秘书长
if there is no evidence,
如果没有证据
I will
那属下
get some.
就去找证据
Captain Wei.
魏队长
Yes, Sir.
属下在
I've been trying to find
我一直想物色一个
the right person to be my assistant
合适的人选
at the military prosecution.
到监察院担任我的助手
The candidate has not been decided.
这个人选迟迟未定
If you can
如果年底之前
enrich your resume
你能让自己的履历
by the end of the year,
更漂亮一些
maybe we will
过完新年
work together at the military prosecution
也许我们就能在监察院
after the New Year.
共事了
I...
属下明